<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvarning to England to repente and to tvrne to god from idolatrie and poperie by the terrible exemple of Calece, giuen the 7. of March. Anno. D. 1558. By Benthalmai Outis.</title>
            <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838237</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838237</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13870)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvarning to England to repente and to tvrne to god from idolatrie and poperie by the terrible exemple of Calece, giuen the 7. of March. Anno. D. 1558. By Benthalmai Outis.</title>
                  <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>P.A. de Zuttere?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted Anno. D. 1558.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Benthalmai Outis = Bartholomew Traheron.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Idolatry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A VVAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING TO ENGLAND TO REPENTE, AND TO TVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to god from idolatrie and poperie by the the terrible exemple of Calece, giuen the 7. of March. Anno. D. 1558.</p>
            <p>BY BENTHALMAI OVTIS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEBR. 13.</bibl>
               <p>Brethern abide the worde of exhortation.</p>
               <bibl>IOEL. 2.</bibl>
               <p>Turne vnto me with al your herte, in faſting, weeping, and lamentation.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶Imprinted Anno. D. 1558.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IF</hi> GOD ALMOST BY MIRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle hath caſt ſo terrible lightnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon Calece, as make, ether al mennes eares to glow, &amp; tingle, or their hertes to tremble, &amp; quake, that heare how ſore that toune is ſodainly plaged, what maieſt thou loke for, ô England, whoſe moſt deteſtable, and moſt abominable hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible vices, ſo far excede the vices of Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, as Sodome euer paſſed Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vilainous tragical actes. For to conſidre this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoroughly, and to beginne with the cheifeſt, the gouernor of Calece did beare in dede with idolatrie, and falſe religion, &amp; therefore is iuſtly brought in to a captiues wretched ſtate. But thy ruler England with raging madnes, and open tyrannie at hir firſt entraunce reſtored in haſt idolatrie and falſe popiſh religion, being before luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely beaten dounne, thorough out the hole realme, and now continueth a ſhameles ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uancer, and bloodie mainteiner of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. The gouernor of Calece ioied not to ſee the people defile them ſelues with vile poperie, with idolatrious maſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, with crouching to domme ſtockes, &amp; ſtones, with kiſſing of canferd croſſes, with
<pb facs="tcp:2604:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſprincling of enchaunted and exchaunted waters vpon their forloren bodies, with ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of charmed bread, in ſtede of Chriſtes holie ſacrament: Thy ruler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth al men to thoſe, and manie other like horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abominations, with thondring threates, and moſt violent flames of fier. The go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernor of Calece erneſtly bewailed in his herte, the decaie of ſound doctrine grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly renued and repared in the daies of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie king Edwarde. Thy ruler reioiſeth, and triumpheth in treading, and ſtamping it vndre hir fete. The gouernor of Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce reuerently ſpake, and thought of true re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion. Thy ruler moſt blaſphemouſly raileth vpon it, and moſt dedly hateth it. The gouernor of Calece kepte his handes pure from ſhedding of innocent blood. Thy ruler hath bathed hir ſelfe, and ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the holie blood of moſt innocent, vertuous, and excellent perſonages. Let the bloodie bodie of the courteous, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, godlie, wiſe, and wel lerned Ladie Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and of the gilteles lord Giltford com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me forth for witneſſes. In noble Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wiat perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and his companie thy ruler maie haue ſome pretence, and yet that
<pb facs="tcp:2604:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> valiaunt capitaine, &amp; right vertuous man, with the reſt of that band, without doubte put on armour, and roſe vp in defence of their countree, which than bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied. And the like maie be ſaide of the good duke of Suffolke, and of that worthie man my lorde Thomas Graie his brother.</p>
            <p>Of whom if anie thing were don amiſſe, thy ruler was the verie autor, headſpring, and principal cauſe of it, and therefore ſtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned hir ſelfe with blood in killi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe faulte, if there were anie, ſhe hir ſelfe cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, bred vp, &amp; brought forth. But what color, or cloke can ſhe haue, if I cal for the burnt bones &amp; aſſhes, of the ſobre lerned, and holie martyr Thomas grammer arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terburie? of the excellent, wiſe godlie, and ſkilful man Nicolas Ridleie biſhop of London, of ſondrie other vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and lerned biſhoppes, and miniſters of goddes worde, and of a nombre of good, ſimple, verie innocent, harmles, and right godlie men, and wemen, whom ſhe hath moſt cruelly roſted, and fried in flames for mainteining the open truth, and keping of their conſcience vpright before god. So that if thou compare hir with the old perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutors
<pb facs="tcp:2604:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of goddes truth Nero, Decius, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocletian, Domitian, Maximine, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt perceaue, that ſhe hath mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the outragious crueltie of them, &amp; that hir extreme tyrannie hath dured lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyrannie of the moſt parte of thother, &amp; in ſome pointes is gonne farther. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of thoſe perſequuted the bones, &amp; aſhes of ded men, nor ſought the further afflicti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and famiſhment of ſuch as by them we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re alreadie driuen out of their natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees, as this, furious tyranneſſe hath don moſt gredely vnnaturally, and vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But to procede in our former compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon, whereby thy ſtate ſhalbe better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, the gouernor of Calece neuer condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned anie, whoſe cauſe he had not heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and perfectly vndreſtanded. Thy ruler hath caſt in to raging fiers more than three hundred vertuous, innocent, godlie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe cauſe ſhe neuer heard, neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſtode, neuer labored to know thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Yea leſt hir conſcience ſhuld condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne hir of moſt horrible murder, and leſt hir bloodie deſire might be dulled, ſhe obſtina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely refuſeth once to loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bokes of excellent good men, which plainly proue,
<pb facs="tcp:2604:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> that only the open truth hath ben the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for which ſo manie holie perſonages muſt ſuffre moſt cruel death. The gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor of Calece mainteined an honeſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, godlie ſeruantes both men, &amp; women.</p>
            <p>Thy ruler hath aboute hir raueners, ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, flatterers, effoeminate Ganimedes, Alcinoes youth, and amonge hir women verie ſtrompettes, and to wel knowen bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and witches. The gouernor of Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce what ſo euer is now forged to cloke the quenes trecherie, and to bleare the peoples eyes, bare a ſingular loue to the toune, and procured the welth of it to his power. Thy ruler not only being warned of imminent daunger left that toune purpoſely ſpoiled of good ſoldiars, and warlike ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge men, to make a waie to hir luſt in meaning to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it vp to another, but hath alſo ſtudied theſe 4. yeres to betraie the ô Englande in to the handes of a ſtraunger, and of a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on moſt defamed in al the world for pride, and crueltie. She hath ſought meanes to make the fight againſt thy ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereby being enfeebled and weakened, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt be leſſe able to reſiſt the force of the ſpaniard. She beganne warre with a migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:2604:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> king, where peace was ſought, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, only to ſatiſfie hir wilful head, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the force of the ſpaniard, &amp; to maim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the of thi beſt capitaines, &amp; ſoldiars. She hath ſpoiled the of thy artillarie, of thy trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and iuels ſent in to a foraine cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree, I thinke no more, for the loue of the ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the hate, that ſhe beareth agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thy people. For bicauſe ſhe hath begon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a thing nawghtely vpon hir awne head, ſhe wil now procede wickedly without ſtaie and extremely hateth al them, as ether like not hir doinges, or by them ſtand in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of deſtruction. And ſhe is ſo bereft of witte, that ſhe thincketh it better, to do madly, and nawghtely ſtil a peaſe, than to ſeme to haue don madly, and nawghtely at the beginninge thorow wilful deſire, &amp; ſhe is now ſunke ſo far in follie, that ſhe wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that ſhe maie wype awaie the blotte of hir firſt madnes with continual purſuite of the ſame Finally the gouernor of Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lece, his cloking, and diſſembling of goddes truth excepte, was a good man, gentle, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, curteous, harmeles, plaine, temperate ſobre, honeſt, and vertuous. Thy ruler is thoroughly ſpotted with papiſtrie, &amp; ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie,
<pb facs="tcp:2604:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> a ſtocke worſhipper, a cakeworſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a bold blaſphemer of the true Chriſt, whoſe bleſſed bodie is gloriouſly placed in heauen, and not pinde in popes pixes. Thy ruler is diſdainful, and ſo proude, that to be the wife of an emperors ſonne, &amp; for hope that ſhe ſhal once be called my ladie empereſſe, ſhe is contente not only to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the as bare as a birdes taile, but alſo vnna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally to betraie the hir natiue countree, &amp; make the ſubiecte to a popiſh proude, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful, and vngodlie nation. She is deſpiteful, cruel, bloodie, wilful, furious, gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leful, ſtuffed with painted proceſſes, with ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mulation, &amp; diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, void of honeſtie, void of vpright dealinge, voide of al ſeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vertues. I ſpeake not this of hatred god I cal to recorde, nor for anie luſte to recompte others lotheſome euils, but only to cal hir to ſpedie repentaunce, by the vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſight of hir moſt horrible ſinnes. I iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſurely that of al other I ought moſt to la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente hir, as the moſt vnfortunate woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that euer was. For whereas beſides the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe deteſtable open, and wel knowen vices, and other more ſecrete fowle ſores, ſhe is giltie of the blood, &amp; damnation of al tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:2604:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that haue periſhed, daily periſh and ſhal periſh thorough the moſt abominable groſſe idolatrie, and falſe religion, that ſhe hath ſette vp, and thorough wante of the true knowlege of Chriſt, which ſhe hath by al meanes poſſible quenched, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet ſhe hath not one that wil warne hir, of the moſt miſerable, and moſt terrible ſtate that ſhe ſtandeth in. Wherefore ſith al hir frendes, and louers, ſhauelinges, and other ſlaues of the poleſhore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwarme with ſilence, and cloſed lippes, ſee hir runne hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in to the lake, that burneth with vnquen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chable fier, I thought it my dutie to do good for euil, and by opening, and laying corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to hir piteful feſtred ſores, to prepare them to a farther cure, that ſhe periſh not euerlaſtingly. And I beſeche god moſt hertely to bring my deſire to effecte, which is ſurely none other, but that hir ſowle, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough the great mercies of god, and hir hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knowleging, hating, and renouncing of hir ſinnes in time, maie be ſaued from hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier. It maie wel be that for this my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhe wil ſeke my death, but ſhe ſhal ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſeke the death of him, that loueth hir better, and wold do more for hir perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb facs="tcp:2604:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſafetie, than al the fatte fed preiſtes, and papiſtes ether in the courte, or in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. And if ſhe knew aſmuch as I do ſhe wold be gladder of the woundes that I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue giuen hir, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al the kiſſes that euer ſhe had in al hir life, firſt, or laſt. For what ſhuld it auaile hir, if with the loſſe of hir ſowle for euer, ſhe might a while poſſeſſe in this world al the ioies together, that ar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined therein. Nothing erthlie wold be bought with euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g torment, which ſhal as certainly comme vpon hir, as god liueth, and is true of his worde, onles before cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral death ſhe repente hir of theſe moſt deteſtable abominat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, that I haue now laied forth, and turne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time from the falſe pope, &amp; patched poperie to the true Chriſt, and tru religion, &amp; be purged, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, not by coniured waters, and mennes phantaſtical deuiſes, but by the holie ſpirite of god. Which grace if god of his infinite goodnes ſhal graunte hir, I wil ſeke no grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter rewarde of my trauail. But lette vs procede in our conſideration, and comme now to the counſel of Calece, one of the cheifeſt whereof, the greateſt ſembler, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembler, the ſubtileſt flatterer that liueth,
<pb facs="tcp:2604:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> called to another office in the courte by the death of a vile nonniſh papiſt, was abſent at the ſubduyng of the toune. That Vlyſſes I ſaie, the deuiſer of miſcheife was abſent, not to auoid, but to runne in to a more hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible plage, onles he preuente it with ſpedie repentance. This is he who in king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes time putte on a maſke, and viſor of a proteſtant, and with his melie mouth, and flering lookes crepte in to good mennes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſomes. This is he, who thorough crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of witte, and by the helpe of a mad calfe begiled the good lord wentworth, &amp; drue him from a better purpoſe, and ſo was the occaſion of al the miſcheife, and miſeries, that haue enſued ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns. Beſides this fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe traitor to god, to his ſrendes, and to his countree, who as I ſaide, was awaie at the ruine of the tounne, the reſt of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of Calece, were not notoriouſly nawghtie men. In the moſt parte of them, a man colde deſire nothinge, ſaue more zeale to the truth, that thei knew, more ſtrenghth of minde, more feare of god than of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For this in dede was a commune faulte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them al, &amp; worthie manie deathes, and vttre deſtruction, that thei ſtode not to the
<pb facs="tcp:2604:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowen truth, but for feare, and to ſatiſfie the wil of an ignorant wilful woman, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred them ſelues to be defiled with abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable maſſe idolatrie, and were contente with grudge of conſcience to ſeme to drinc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in againe al the popes filthie dregges. Certaine of them were papiſtes to, I wote wel, and yet thei retained ſome ciuilite, and outwarde honeſtie. Turne thyne eyes now to thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel England, how fierce ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres, how cruel wolues, how rauening bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, how lecherous goates how wilie foxes, or to ſpeake plainly without figure, what periured traitors to god, and to the, what murderers, what oppreſſors of the poore, what voluptuous Sardanapales, what adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, how vile flatterers ſhalt thou finde amonge them? It were a ſmal faulte, and a verie peccadulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them to diſſemble the truth of religion. Thei raile vpon it, they toſſe it with ſcoffes &amp; mockes, thei bloode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nouſly perſequute it. It might be wicked at, if thei toke bribes, o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to oppreſſe the cauſe of a few poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei take bribes to betraie the hole realme. It might be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer with ſilence if thei had murdered but one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a peece, the blood of innumera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſainctes crieth vp to heauen agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt them
<pb facs="tcp:2604:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; the groninges of manie thouſandes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ar heard euerie where. It might perchaunce be perdoned, if they ſpent but ſome weekes in pleaſures, they wallow con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually in vile voluptuouſnes, and wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daliance, and waſte al their vnhappie daies in beaſtlie delites, nether can chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor women only ſatiſfie their filthie abominable deſires. Breifely there be no vices in the world whereof you maie not ſee great buddes, or rather great bounnies, and bunches in them. Here I maie not let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſcape the priſtes of Calece, a foule broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of thy henne. Papiſtes they were and verie furies of hel. But if thei be compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to thy prelates and preiſtes, thei were but demipapiſtes, and demidiuels. For he that wold diſcouer the fowle inwarde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of thy ſhauelinges, and filthie ſmered flocke, ſhuld ſeme to rake vp the botome of hel, yea he that wold ſhew the outwarde par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of them naked, ſhuld ſhew the fowleſt ſight, that euer was ſene in the world. For what idolatrie, what pride, what couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what crueltie, what lecherie, what ſodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitrie, was euer heard of in anie age, that thei haue not far exceded? Thou canſt
<pb facs="tcp:2604:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> not name a biſhoppe, but thou ſhalt ſee his tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſwollen with blaſphemie, his fingers dropping with the blood of innocentes, his bodie ſpotted with moſt filthie villanie, &amp; the reſt of thy AEgyptian ſhauelinges, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue which ſhal paſſe other farthieſt in al kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of beaſtlie abomination. And to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke as I thinke, amonge them, Weſton, who hath worne, and weried himſelfe in whore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom, theſe twentie yeres, and now for his late chaſt behauior is iudged to leeſe his ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, maie be compted an honeſt man. So manifolde, ſo execrable, ſo outragious is their filthines, and wickednes. Who can thinke on that bloodie beaſt Bonner, but a moſt griſlie, vgle, &amp; horrible monſtre ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be preſented before his eyes, ſuch a one as no Polyphemus in boiſteouſnes, no furies of hel with their ſnakie heares in al poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of miſcheife, no Cerberus in blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous roaring, no find in raging, in tearing, and in deuouring innocentes, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouermat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. But I wil leaue that botomeles ſea, of moſt filthie ſtincking vices, &amp; paſſe farther. The commons of Calece conſiſted partely of papiſtes, and partely of men reformed in religion. The papiſtes were there, as
<pb facs="tcp:2604:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> they be euerie where, murmurers againſt god gredie ſcrapers, enuious, lecherous, ful of ſecrete vices, but they were few in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, and leſſe beſprincled with innocent blood. The Chriſtianes were weaklinges, diſſemblers, quenepleaſers, worldlinges, riotous, wanton, &amp; giuen to al fleſhlie luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for the moſt parte. I comme now to thy commons England, of which ſome be gentle men, &amp; thoſe ether papiſtes, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes. The papiſtical gentle men ar ſlaues to poleſhorne preiſtes, to exequute their boucherie, folowing therein parte of thy nobilitee, in bloodie crueltie worſe than Shythians, in oppreſſing the poore Neroes helliſh ofſpringe, in greedie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes verie Harpyes, in malice, and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uie yonge diuels, traitors to their countree, open deceauers, vile flatterers, filthie le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, herteles cowardes, ſhameles brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, godles Epicures. The gentle men ptoteſtantes for the moſt parte differ from thother in knowlege only, and not in life, in wordes, and not in worckes. The life conuetouſnes, the like malice, and enuie, the like craftines, the like cowardiſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faithfulnes in defending their countree, the
<pb facs="tcp:2604:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> like flatterie, the like lecherie, the like dronc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes in fleſhlie pleaſures, the like liynge is found in both ſortes. And the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne people to be ſhorte ſo countrefaite the beaſtlie, and abominable maners of theyr ſuperiors, that they maie be compted their awne children, their awne brode aſwel as their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tremen, I ſpeake of the great multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude. For I know that in euerie ſorte, and condition of men, there be ſome that truly feare god. But in the ordre of thy nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litee al the godlie maie be grauen in one ringe. Amonge thy prelates, and preiſtes I know not one, and yet I exclude not al of that moſt filthie ſwineſtie. Amonge thy gentlemen there be ſo few, that wold god the tithes, yea the twentithes, yea the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes might be ſanctified to god, as men en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dued with ſome litle ſparcke of feare towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des him. Amonge the commune peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vndoubtedly there be more, but thei ar oppreſſed, and drouned in the huge multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; infinite ſwarmes of nawghtie wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men. Sith than that beiond nombre, and meaſure thou excedeſt Calece in ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragiouſnes, and multitude of moſt miſche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous factes, &amp; horrible vices, what thought
<pb facs="tcp:2604:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> canſt thou haue to eſcape the preſent drad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vengeance of god, which thou haſt ſo manie waies deſerued, and daily prouokeſt to be powred vpon the. For thou art not ſo witles, and ſtarcke mad, as to thincke that welth, artillarie, or force of men can driue backe the vehement tempeſtes of plages, that haſt to hurle the doune. For what power can ſtaie god, whan he wil ſtrike, or anie thinge at al draw backe his heauie han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. And beſides that, though riches, and force might helpe, as thei can not, yet thou art altogether vnfurniſhed. For thou art brought to verie beggerie. Thy beſt ordinance is loſt, giuen, or conueighed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie. Thy capitaines ar purpoſely mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, or pined awaie thorough thought of thy ruine. Thy noble men ar ether ſtarcke cowardes, or ſtarcke fooles for the moſt parte, and more meete for their effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatenes to handle a ſpindle, than to bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a ſpeare, Thy commune people tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough pouertie, and continual miſerie ar hertles more readie to beare burthens, and packes on their wretched ſhulders, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on their manlie backes. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth than ô moſt miſerable countree?
<pb facs="tcp:2604:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie other thinge be looked for, but waſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of fruteful fildes, burni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of cities, &amp; tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, ſlawghter vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlawghter, murdering of infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in their mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes, death befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re life, deflowri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of virgines rauiſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, a worſe life than death it ſelfe in them that ſhal remaine vnmurdered, haling, har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng, &amp; tugging hither, and thither by the heare of the head, miſerable captiuitee, vile ſlauerie, and al kindes of extreme, and moſt intolerable oppreſſions. O yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the infinite heape of thy deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſertes, heare what thy god ſaieth. For thus he ſpeaketh vnto the, vnto the I ſaie, if thou wilt yet giue eare by the mouth of his holie prophete Ieremie in 3. chap. Returne thou backe ſlidden Iſrael, &amp; I wil not make myn anger to fal vpon the. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me times thou waſt goddes Iſrael, goddes holie congregation, and ſanctified people. For the pure worde of god ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded euerie where in the, his ſacramentes were rightly adminiſtred, image ſeruice, ſuperſtition, &amp; al pilde peſtilent poperie was clearely ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, newnes of life, and the goodlie fair bloſomes of goddes ſpirite in manie were wel ſeen. But now thou art ſlidden, and hast
<pb facs="tcp:2604:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> taken a fowle fal. For in ſtede of goddes worde thou haſt now mennes doting drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, in ſtede of Chriſtes ſwete goſpel the popes ſower draffe, inſtede of Chriſtes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende ſupper, the popes toiy ſhapes plaie and monkiſſhe munming maſſe, in ſtede of goddes true ſeruice, thou haſt ſtocke ſeruice, bone ſeruice, and wafer ſeruice. For right holines of ſpirite, thou haſt a countrefaite popeholines, that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in butter forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in fiſh feaſting, in fleſh fliyng, with mouth, not with minde, in wymple wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in graie coate gatting, in lowring, in whimpering, in howling, in prating to pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted poſtes, in biyng of blaſphemous bulles, breifely for al vertues, thou haſt embraced al vices. The wittie poetes faine, that Ix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion wold adulterouſly haue laine with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, which thing Iuppiter hir huſband per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing turned a cloude in to hir likenes, which cloude Ixion haſted with great fond ioie, to embraſe in ſtede of his peramour.</p>
            <p>Hath not the like, or a thing far worſe hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened vnto the? Haſt not thou catched after clowdes, and vaine ſhadowes in ſtede of the truth not only whereby thou haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de thy ſelfe a lawghi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſtocke to al the world
<pb facs="tcp:2604:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> as Ixio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo moſt furiouſly pulled vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, the heauie indignation of almightie god. Thou haſt in dede gon a whoring and committed adulterie with ſtockes and ſtones, &amp; thinne weeriſch bread, while thou woldeſt ſeme to folow the true ſpouſe, &amp; to ſeke his ſpiritual embraſinges, and, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby thou haſt deſerued confuſion, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting damnation. And yet for al this thy god, and moſt louing huſband, biddeth the turne againe to him, and he wil ſtaie his iuſt indignation. O refuſe not, as a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate mad woman, to heare his ſwete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and gratious voice. Repente, and deteſte thy vnkindnes, thy filthines, &amp; beaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie abomination, Awaie with thy wafer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goddes, with thy maſking maſſes, with thy latine mumbling, with thy loſt liplabor.</p>
            <p>Awaie with thy lies, and falſe ſacrificing for the quicke &amp; the ded, the greateſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before god that euer was deuiſed. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie with thy coniured water, and charmed bread. Awaie with thy proud pompous pope, and al his peſtiferous poperie.</p>
            <p>Awaie with thy ſtincking lecherie, bocher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie crueltie, greedie catching, wretched ſparing. Awaie with thy pride ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
<pb facs="tcp:2604:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> enuie, and malice, that maſſe of a miſchiefe, that hangeth on thy fleſh, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne at the laſt to thy moſt gratious huſband whoſe fauor is as the due in the morning to drie withered herbes, whoſe diſpleaſure is moſt doleful death. Dimnes, &amp; darcknes deſperation, and anguiſh, al horrible miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, and calamities, death and deſtruction draw faſt on, which al thou maieſt yet auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, if thou wilt turne at the louing calling of thy moſt merciful lorde. Calece was called, and wold not heare, and therefore is beaten low, and ſore preſſed with goddes plage, and ſhalt thou eſcape, if thou deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the like calling, in ſo great apparance of deſtruction. For there was no ſuch like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihode of miſerie ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging ouer Calece, whan ſhe was called, as there is now a ful ſight of vttre ruine haſting towardes the. Thou art now warned by me, and waſt longe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens warned by the notable prophete of god maſter Latimer, and thou art moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly warned by the terrible oppreſſion of Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lece. The cuppe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt nedes be double mixte, that thou ſhalt drincke vp dregges and al, and in compariſon of thy miſerie the beating of Calece ſhal ſeme a benifite.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Loke vpon ſtories, and thou ſhalt finde, that thoſe realmes haue euer ben ſoreſt pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged that were moſt warned, and wold not repente Nether the criynges of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, nor the ruine of Samaria, cold cal Ieruſalem to repentance. Wherefore the plages, ſorowes, and miſeries that rained doune by heapes vpon Ieruſalem, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable, and excedingly paſſed the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calamities of Samaria. Thou than ô Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, if thou haue anie pitie on thy ſelfe, on thy grave headded fathers, on thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue matrones, on thy ſwete children, on thy ſemelie maidens, and towardlie youth, ſhake of al ſluggiſchnes, ſeke no vaine ſhiftes flatter not thy ſelfe in thy wickednes, heare not the blaſphemous bluſtering of thoſe helhoundes, that impute the loſſe of Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to the neglecting of poperie, as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in S. Auguſtines times affirmed, that the forſaking, and deſpicyng of theyr old goddes, and goddeſſes, was the cauſe of the decaie, and ruine of the empire. Which theyr ſhameles, and abominable affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, god incontinently reuenged, with the ouerthrow, ſacking, and burning of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the imperial citie. The like talke now
<pb facs="tcp:2604:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> I wotte wel ſtreameth out of the fowle mouthes of thy babilonical prelates. For where as thei thorough their trecherie haue, euer wrought the deſtruction &amp; vttre rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of tounes cities, &amp; countrees, as the loſſe of al Aſia, and of a great parte of Africa, &amp; Europe doeth ouermuch teſtifie, they yet pleaſe them ſelues in their outragious miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife, and wil rather fight againſt god, &amp; aſcribe the miſeries of the world to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des faulte, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thei wil acknowlege the verie cauſe of al plages in dede, namely their awne extreme horrible wickednes.</p>
            <p>And it is no meruail, if they wold haue the profeſſing, and preaching of the goſpel to ſeme the cauſe of the realmes ſhame, loſſe and decaie. For they hate no poiſon in the world ſo much, as they hate, and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re goddes word, and his truth. For that bewraieth their hypocriſie, their idolatrie, their falſe doctrine, their fine deuiſes their traitorous counſels, breifely al their ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te abominations. That vndermineth their popes throne, pulleth their mitres fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heades, breaketh their crociars<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> chaſeth them not only out of kinges counſels, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they occupie the cheife places, the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:2604:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> nobilitee beinge hoiſted out, but alſo from houſe, and home, and maketh them deteſtable to al the world. And therefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they care not by what meanes thei defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me it. But heare not thou their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous bellowing, and helliſhe roaring, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidre rather thy woful ſtate, and meaſure thy ſelfe with thine awne fote, looke vpon thy faultes with thine awne eyes, and not with their falſe ſpectacles, acknowlege as the truth is iuſte cauſes of al miſerie to be in thy ſelfe, not for receauing, but for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing true doctrine once plainly preached vnto the, not for renouncyng of vile pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but for eating of it in eftſones, whan thou haddeſt once caſt it vp, not for thy ſwimming out of the myre of filthie vices, but for thy returning, and wallowing in to the ſame againe. Heape not ſinne vpon ſinne with ſhameles ſhifting. Nether yet for al this let thy ruler falle to deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhal ſee no color of excuſe, no ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hoale in ſo great a multitude of furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es meeting hir in euerie corner. Let hir not ſaie in hir herte, who ſhal waſche my bloodie handes? Who ſhal clenſe my ſow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ful of leproſie? Who ſhal wipe awaie
<pb facs="tcp:2604:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſpottes of my idolatrie, witchcraft, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, traitorous deuiſes, proud thoughtes, filthie deſires, longe continued hatred, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and enuie? How ſhal I eſcape the ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geance to comme, how ſhal I abide the face and preſence of god, whoſe ſainctes I haue partely burnt to aſhes, partely tormented in priſons, partely robbed of their landes, and goodes, &amp; ſondrie wiſe cruelly afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whoſe ſpirite I haue dotingly accuſed of hereſie, whoſe word I haue defamed, &amp; railed vpon, as new doctrine, &amp; chaſed out of al churches, whoſe people generally I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue defrauded and ſpoiled of the bread of life, and haue cauſed them to be miſerably fed with the popes ſluttiſch vnſauerie ſop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, with ſtincking mingle mangle, and ded<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie dregges. Let not thy nobilitee, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons ſaie, our ſinnes ar greater than that thei maie be forgeuen. Let thy ruler ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te kinge Manaſſe before hir eyes, of whom it is firſt written that he builded vp chapel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of idolatrie, that he cauſed his awne ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to paſſe thorough fier, that he maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſorcerers, witches, and enchaunters, that he filled al the corners of Ieruſalem with in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nocent blood, and neuertheles afterward
<pb facs="tcp:2604:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> this foloweth of him in the 33. cha. of the 2. boke of chro. Whan Manaſſe was in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, he entreated the face of the lord his god, and humbled him ſelfe exceedingly in the ſight of the god of his fathers. And whan he praied to him, he was entreated, &amp; appeaſed, and he heard his praier, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red him to his kingdom, &amp; Manaſſe acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leged, that Iehoua was god. Lette this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the ſinful herte of thy ruler.</p>
            <p>Let thy nobilitee, and commons remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre the Niniuites, which were al heathen, al idolatres, and therefore al wicked men, and yet repentinge vpon the preaching of Ionas thei eſcaped the imminent plages of god, and preſent deſtruction. If thy preiſtes and prelates, or anie other haue perſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the knowen truth, of verie malice, and deſpite againſt god, and ſo ſinned againſt the holie goſt, let them die in their ſinnes, &amp; periſh euerlaſtingly. Let the reſt thincke this ſpoken vnto them: thou haſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whoredom with manie companions, but turne vnto me, ſaieth the lorde. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto me backe ſlidden children, and I wil be your lorde, I wil receaue you, and bring you to Sion. Let them than with al ſpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:2604:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and humilitee of herte fal dounne flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te before the lord, holde vp their handes to heauen, aſke mercie, and turne to their lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing lord to the true Chriſt, who calleth them not out of a cankerd braſen boxe, or out of a peece of foiſtie ſtarche, but from his glorious celeſtial palace, lette them embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe his goodnes gratiouſly offred. Lette them kyſſe the ſonne of god, louingly com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming towardes them, and after their vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural behauior, after their exceding great vnkindnes, after their longe continued ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulteries, bending doune his heauenlie head, and offring his ſwete diuine mouthe vnto them. Lette them reuerently receaue him, lette them reuerently receaue him, I ſaie, leſt his anger ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly kendle, and thei periſh, be ſtricken with light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninges fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and confounded for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶A VVARNING TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>VVHo ſoeuer thou art, whoſe lotte it ſhalbe to reade this admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinke not fondly that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hereof, wold ſerue his affections in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing mennes vices, or thereby delight him ſelfe, or other mennes eares, or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hatred to anie ſtate, or anie perſon, and blow a trompette to malice. For ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubte thou ſhalt fowly begile thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, diſpleaſe god highly, and leeſe the frute of his trauail in writing, and of thy time in reading. But aſſure thy ſelfe, that he hath ſpared no condition, and ſtate in this great, and weightie matter, for none other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſaue only to moue al ſortes to repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce, ſeing plainly the hole ſtaie of the realme now ſhaking, and threatening a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, to reſt therevpon. And if thou ſhalt vſe this nedeful warning to anie other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, than to amende thy ſelfe, and to ſtirre other to amendment of life, and to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of goddes glorie, thou ſhalt tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente the herte of the writer, diſturbe the holie deſires of the gdolie, &amp; pulle the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb facs="tcp:2604:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> of god vpon thine awne head. Nether on thother ſide be thou ſo weake, as to thinke that the autor ſhuld haue forbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to haue vttred al that he ether knew him ſelfe to be true, or had lerned of other, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the nobilitee of the perſonages, but conſidre that it becamme him in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cauſe, and in a matter touching the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or vttre ruine of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree, to haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde rather to the welth, &amp; preſeruation, than to the honor of the perſons, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if thei continue in their wickednes, the hole realme muſt certainly comme in daunger of goddes wrath, and vnrecouerable deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction. Walke thoue therefore vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; be nether to wordly wiſe, nor to word<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fooliſh, nether haſtie to hate, nor ſlacke to redreſſe bothe thy ſelfe, and other, but praie with this writer that god of his infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te goodnes wil vouchſafe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerte the, thy ruler, thy nobilitee, and al other thy countre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men from wickednes of life, &amp; from al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe ſuperſtition, and idolatrie vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that yet his people maie be herboured in Englande, that yet his goſpel maie ſounde, and haue free courſe in Englan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that yet his holie name maie there be
<pb facs="tcp:2604:16"/> magnified, and aduaunced in peace, and quietnes.</p>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <q>
               <bibl>LVKE 13.</bibl>
               <p>THINKE YE THAT THESE GALILAEANS VVERE SIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERS ABOVE AL OTHER BICAVSE THEI HAVE SVF<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>FRED SVCH THINGES. NO I SAIE VNTO YOV, BVT ONLES YOV REPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TE YOV SHAL AL PERISH LIKE VVISE ETC.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:17"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:18"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device (not in McKerrow) of a tree with a serpent, a crucifix, a field of corn or wheat, and a figure below a banner with Greek lettering</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprinted Anno Domini 1558.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2604:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
